<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tidings of peace, or, Acure [sic] for the many evills that happen in the world about religion in a discourse of the new Jerusalem ...</title>
            <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27631</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2182</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14651</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13589306</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13589306</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100647</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27631)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100647)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 783:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tidings of peace, or, Acure [sic] for the many evills that happen in the world about religion in a discourse of the new Jerusalem ...</title>
                  <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Utrecht :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100647:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100647:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> TIDINGS of PEACE, <hi>OR</hi> Acure for the many Evills that happen in the world about Religion, in a diſcourſe <hi>OF</hi> The New Jeruſalem, <hi>Proveing</hi> That The New Jeruſalem is a Holy Citty to be built on Earth in each Kingdom, in which The Clergie are to dwell; Whereby a New and moſt happy <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Adminiſtration</hi> will ariſe.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Behold I will bring it Health and Cure and I will Cure Them, and I will Reveal unto Them abundance of Peace and Truth. <bibl>Jer. 33: v. 6.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And I Iohn Saw The Holy Citie the New Jeruſalem, comeing downe from God out of Heaven, prepared as a Bride adorned for her husband. <bibl> Rev. 21: v. 2.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And Hee that ſate upon the Throne, ſaid Behold I make all things <bibl>New. v. 5.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100647:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100647:2"/>
            <head>To the Clergie.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>S<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Dedication of the enſueing Modell of the Holy Citty doth moſt properly belong to you, as being the Lords Heritage and Servants: In the old Adminiſtration, The Sons of Aron had Thirteene Cittyes and the Levites eight and Fourty, but in the New and better Adminiſtration the Servants of Jeſus haue not one Citty to dwell in amongſt all the Kingdomes of the Earth. <q>Methinks I heare you Speaking as the Sons of the Prophets to Eliſha viz<hi rend="sup">t</hi>: Loe the Place where wee dwell is to ſtrait for us, Let us goe unto Jordan and take thence every one a beame, and Lett us make a Place there where wee may dwell.</q> Tis certaine your Place is to Strait, and though Some of you haue roome too much, yet others (unhappy unequallity) haue noe Place at all. I could Preſent you with a Catalogue of all the Evills you haue ſuffered for many yeares, and of the many evills<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the world hath ſufferd by you. But <hi>Prima abiêrunt, &amp; Ecce nova facio omnia,</hi> Old Things are paſſed away, and loe I make all things New, Saith Chriſt in the Revel: I ſhall omit mentioning the forma Evills and proceed to the remedying of them. And doe here preſent you with a modell of a New OEconomie, and tis this. I haue appointed you a Citty in each Nation and Kingdome to dwell in, where in you ſhalle liue peaceably and quietly, and ſhall be ſufficiently provided for of all things neceſſary for your holy Functions, ſoe that all Temptations ſhall be taken away from you of acting or moveing irregularly; From this Citty placed in the midſt' of each Nation, you are to goe or ride out, as it ſhall pleaſe you, every month by turnes, and heale each Nation, and on the Bells of your horſes ſhall be wrote <hi>Holyneſſe to the Lord.</hi> The Kings &amp; Princes of the world and all Temporall Governments will find their acco<hi rend="sup">tt</hi>. in building
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100647:3"/> you ſuch a Citty, for tis not to be expreſſed what happineſſe will accrue to them and to all the world thereby: This Citty will put an end to all the miſeryes the World labours under on account of Religion And wee ſhall heare from you rideing on your Red, white, and Speckled Horſes that Joyfull Report mentioned in the 1<hi rend="sup">ſt</hi>. cap. of the Prophet Zach<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. &amp; 11. verſe. <hi>Wee haue walked to and fro thorow the Earth, and behold all the Earth ſitteth ſtill and is at Reſt.</hi> If this be the glorious effects of your circular Preaching as wee haue all the reaſon in the world to thinke it will. Tis no wonder that the Kings of the Earth will bring their Glory and honour into this Citty, not onely as it is a Citty dedicated to the honour of God, but as it is a Citty whoſe Inhabitans will eſtabliſh Peace and Tranquillitty in their Kingdoms. It was in the heart of King David, to build God a Houſe, and though God had not commanded it, yet he moſt graciouſly accepted his good intentions. But it has not yet been in the heart of any King to build God a Citty they haue built themſelues Cittyes for their owne honour and glory. Is not this Great Babylon that I have built for the Houſe of the Kingdome, by the might of my Power and for the honour of my Maj<hi rend="sup">tye</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thus ſpeakes the proud Emperour Nebuchadnezzar, and he ſpoake rhe truth, he had built Babell for the honour of his Maj<hi rend="sup">ty</hi>. And many are the Cittyes, whieh both the Heathen and Chriſtian Emperours haue built for their owne honour, and haue put uppor them their owne Names, as Caeſarea, Allexandria, Conſtantinople, &amp;c. but wee find not one by the Name of Deople or Chriſtople. When I conſider how in a ſpeciall manner Gods hath ſet Crownes on many Chriſtian Princes heades, and has raiſed ſome from a Private ſtation to the higheſt dignity, and giuen them Severall Kingdomes and many Thouſand Cittyes, I ſay when I conſider this, it makes me wonder, to find none returning back one ſingle Citty by way of gratitude to the Donour. <hi>Pudet haec opprobria nobis &amp;c.</hi> Tis True They haue built and ginen him Severall Houſes, But what is a Houſe or a few Houſes A magnificent and Royall Citty would be more Suitable to the Maj<hi rend="sup">tie</hi> of Heaven and Earth then a Houſe? Beſides in this Citty he hath ſaid ſhall be noe Temple, plainely inſinuateing that the Temple Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration ſhould be ended and be changed into that of a Citty. To me it ſeemes to be a moſt Juſt and reaſonable Thing That in Every Nation and Kingdom God the Giuer and Governour of all ſhould haue one Citty built and dedicated to his Honour, wherem his Seruants who wait in his Courts and Miniſter at the Altar ſhould be honourably provided for, that their Lineings and fortunes may noe more be precarions, and ſubject to the Will of men, as to the Shame of Chriſtianity they are at this day. I could men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion what evill hath befaln the World on accont of Gods Miniſters being-choſen by men and not by Lot, and by haueing their allowance and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance from Man, but I ſhall here omit it haueing ſpoaken of it in another
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100647:3"/> place. I could heartily wiſh that Chriſtian Kings and Princes and all Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Governments would Seriouſly conſider on this Point. Who can tell but that their building Such a Citty, in which the Diſpenſers of Gods Graces and Bleſſings to each Nation, may dwell, may be as Sweet incenſe in the Noſtrills of God in and ſome meaſure attone him, to ſtop the Rage of Fire and Sword which at preſent layes ſomany of their owne Cittyes waſt? I will hope there fore, That (as Dauid Thought of building Gods a Houſe) ſoe that Some King or other, whom God ſhall deliner from many Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and beſtow on him Crownes and victory over his Enimyes, and ſhall Eſtabliſh him on his Throne in Peace, will thinke of ſo holy a worke, and with a moſt gratefull heart build a Royall Citty to the God of Heaven, as a Pattern and Example to other Princes. And tis my oppinion that That Prince who firſt ſets his hand to ſo holy a worke will as far exceed all others, as a Citty ſhall exceed a houſe or Temple, T'or as Soloman exceed all other Kings of his Time. To you Therefore the Preachers of the Goſpell who are to be Inhabiters of this Citty, To you, whoſe intereſts are ſoe unhappily mixt in Temporalls, To you who haue beene ſoe much abuſed, and who haue abuſed ſo much, To you who are, and haue beene ſoe unhappily and unequally provided for in this Late Adminiſtration, I addreſſe my ſelfe; And make it my Requeſt, that inſtead of writeing, diſputing and Preaching one againſt another, and inſtead of makeing partyes and Factions, and ſtirring up Kings and Princes and the Particular States where you dwell to defend your Controverſyes and intereſts; That you rather apply your ſelves to diſpoſe and move the Hearts of Prince and People to the building you a Citty, wherein you may liue peaccably, and out of w<hi rend="sup">en</hi>. you may with eaſe and Comfort diſpence the pure word of God to Each Nation. This will be more for the Honour of God, for your intereſt and happineſſe, and for the intereſt peace and Happineſſe of each King and People. And who then is willing to conſecrate his Service this day unto the Lord? The 1 Cron. 29 cap. &amp; 5 verſe. This to me ſeemes to be a more pleaſing Text then, Curſe ye Meros, or Some others that I could Name, I recommend you to the Demonſtration of Truth in the modell of the Citty and followeing Pages, and will not further adde, onely when your Citty is built, and you are in your Poſſeſſions, I hope you will be very Thanke full to God, ands not be alltogether unmindfull of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Humble Servant</hi> T. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100647:4"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:100647:4"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od ſaith by the Prophet Iſaiah, Behold! I create a New Heaven and a New Earth &amp;c. in the 56 Cap. &amp; the 17 verſe: And from thence in the 18: 19: &amp; 20 verſes. The Prophet proceeds to deſcribe the happineſſe of the Jewes in this promiſed ſtate; And in the 21: verſe further Saith, And They ſhall build Houſes, and inhabite them, and They ſhall plant Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyards, and eat the fruit of them &amp;c. Now in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven there is neither building, nor planting, ſo that this New Heaven and New Earth can meane nothing elſe but a New and happy ſtate of affaires here uppon Earth. Further in Heaven our Saviour ſaith that there is neither eating, nor drinking, marrying nor giveing in marriage, but that men ſhall be there, as the Angells of God. So that I am ſattisfied there will be no Citties there. If wee are to haue Cities then, wee muſt haue them on Earth, Now I find two Cities, one in the Proph: Ezek. The other in the Revelation of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. John. I ſhall leave ſpeaking of the firſt to the Jewes, and onely treate of this latter, which indeed is very glorious. Without all doubt the meaning is certaine. For in the 22 cap. &amp; 6 verſe. tis ſaid. <hi>Theſe ſayings are faith full and true. And the Lord God of the Holy Prophets ſent his Angell, to ſhew unto his ſervants the things which muſt ſhortly be done,</hi> But how and where theſe things are to be <hi>done,</hi> and what the meaning of this Holy Cittie ſhould be, is the ſubject of my preſent Enquiry. Some wil haue it to be Heaven, and when ever this New Jeruſalem is ſpoaken of, that is <hi>Heaven</hi> ſay They; Others will haue it a repreſentation of the Church purely, and others of a new Condition and happy ſtate of the Church. But there is not one thinkes in the leaſt of it's being a Citty to be built uppon Earth. Firſt then, as to thoſe that thinke it Heaven, I anſwer that without all doubt Heaven in a Spirituall ſence is the New Jeruſalem, but it doth not at all follow that the New Jeruſalem is Heaven, eſpetially this New Jeruſalem, for it may be a Citty built in the Place where the old Jeruſalem was, or another Citty built in another place like the old Jeruſalem either in the Modell, or Serving the Same Ends and deſignes, and for any of theſe reaſons may be called the New Jeruſalem. Beſides this New Jeruſalem is ſaid to come from God <hi>out</hi> of Heaven, therefore cannot be Heaven it ſelfe. This is a plaine confutation of all thoſe who
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100647:5"/> thinke it Heaven. Further it is ſaid, that the Nations of them w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>. are Saved ſhall walke in the light of it, And that the Kings of the Earth ſhall bring their Glory and honour unto it, Now it is certaine that the Kings of the Earth can bring noe Glory or honour into Heaven, but rather receine glory from thence, from God Who is the Fountaine of all honour and Glory; It ſeemes plaine therefore that this New Jeruſalem is not Heaven it ſelfe, and at beſt can onely be ſomething that is a Type of Heaven, What can it then be? it cannot be onely a bare repreſentation of the Church, The compariſon, and Circumſtances will not in the leaſt quadrate, it has toomuch order and beauty in it, to repreſent any thing wee at preſent haue, or hitherto haue had, in the Church: The Church hitherto is rather repreſented to us by a Woman in the Wilderneſſe perſecuted by the Dragon Then by ſuch a Glorious Citty as this is. Nor can Wee Suppoſe that Such a Glorious Citty can be built uppon Earth in a Literall Senſe with ſuch coſtly Materialls. What therefore can the meaning and import of This Citty be, <hi>onely</hi> to repreſent to us the beauty and glory of Heaven and of the Church Triumphant? No, not this <hi>onely.</hi> Yet I muſt acknowledge in part it doth repreſent the Same but not wholly. for Tis attended with too many particular Circumſtances relating to things here below, then wholly and intirely to ſignifie that; it muſt be ſomething which at the firſt appearence in the World muſt ſeeme to Strike and make impreſſion on the Sences of Men. For S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iohn ſaith, <hi>And Iſaw the Holy Citty The New Ieruſalem comming downe from God out of Heaven, prepared as a Bride adorned for her Husband.</hi> That my Modell is ſuch I will not ſay. But This is my Sence of the Whole matter. That The New Heaven and the New Earth mentioned by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iohn doth repreſent a New and Glorious Condition of Church and State, And That this New and glorious Condition will be procured by meanes and influence of this New Jeruſalem, And that This New Jeruſalem is a Citty to be built uppon Earth, after the Same Modell and Form as The Angell hath deſcribed, except the coſtlyneſſe, which as Iſaid before cannot be fullfilled here on Earth; And This Citty ſeemes to me by the Angell to be repreſented ſoe coſtly and Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in part to Typifie to us the Glory of Heaven and of the Church Triumphant; and in part to inſtigate us to build it in the beſt manner wee can; And in part to inſinuate to us, thoſe Glorrious Effects which This New Jeruſalem will produce in the World, introduceing a New and moſt happy OEconomie: Its Inhabitans are to be <hi>Angeli Evangelizantes</hi> Preachers of the Goſpell, and every Monrh, are to goe out and Heale The Nation, for Proofe herof peruſe the following Texts of Scripture And He That ſate upon the Throne ſaid <hi>Behold, I make all Things New.</hi> Johns Revel the 21 cap. &amp; 5 verſe, This relates to the New Adminiſtration, which I hereafter prove in thoſe things that are changeable, in this world. <hi>And it came to paſſe that he went throughout Every Citty and Village, preaching and ſhewing the Glad Tideings of the Kingdome of God, and the Twelve were with him.</hi> Luc. 8. verſe 1. <hi>And Ieſus went about all the Cittyes and Villages, teaching in their Synagogues, and Preaching the Doctrine of the Kingdome</hi> &amp;c. Mat. 9 cap. vers 35. Lo; this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100647:5"/> was the Method Our Saviour tooke when on Earth, And can the Diſciples imitate a better Coppy then their Maſters? And tis certaine that Doctrine wil be beſt nouriſhed and perſerved by the way, and Method it was firſt planted. <hi>I Haue Set Watchmen uppon Thy Walls which ſhall never hold their Peace day nor night. Iſaiah</hi> 62. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. <hi>Thy Watchmen ſhal Lift up the voice, with the voice together ſhall they ſing, for they ſhall See Eye to Eye when The Lord ſhall bring againe Zion the</hi> 52 <hi>Cap.</hi> 8 <hi>vers. And I will ſet Shepheards over them that ſhall feed them, and they ſhall feare no more nor be dismayed, neither ſhall they be lacking ſaith the Lord</hi> Jer. 23: 4: Then againe God ſaith by his Proph: Jer. 3 &amp; 15 verſe. <hi>And I will gine you Paſtours according to my heart, which ſhall feed you with Knowledge and underſtanding.</hi> The Paſtours of this Adminiſtration which are to goe out of the City every month to heale the Nation, ſeem to mee to be the Paſtours here mentioned. The Proph. Zac. the 14: &amp; 8. ſaith thus, <hi>And it ſhall be in that day that Liveing waters ſhall goe out from Jeruſalem, halfe of them towards the former Sea, and halve of them towards the hinder Sea in ſummer and in winter ſhall it be.</hi> Can any thing more plainely chalk out the Method of this new Adminiſtration then this Text? The liueing waters are Preachers, which are to goe out of this Citty in their courſes, Some one way and ſome another both in Summer and in Winter, that is for ever to the worlds end, for ſo long will Summer and in Winter laſt. But as to theſe liueing waters theſe Evangelicall Preachers heare what the Prophet Ezek. in the 47 cap. beginning at the 6: verſe. <hi>Then he brought me and cauſed me ro returne to the brink of the River. Now when I had returned, Behold at the Banke of the River were very many Trees on the one ſide, and on the other. Then ſaid he unto me, Theſe waters iſſue out toward the Eaſt Country, and goe downe into the deſert, and goe into the Sea, which being brought forth into the Sea, the Waters ſhall be healed. And it ſhall come to paſſe, that every thing that Liveth that moveth, whither ſoever the Rivers ſhall come, ſhall live, and there ſhall be a very great multitude of Fish, becauſe theſe Waters (Theſe Preachers) ſhall come thither: for they ſhall be healed, and every thing ſhall liue where the River commeth. And it ſhall come to Paſſe, That the Fiſhers ſhall ſtand uppon it from Engedi even unto Eneglaim: There shall be a Place to ſpread forth Netts, Their fish shall be according to their Kindes as the Fish of the Great Sea exceeding many. But the myrie places therof, and the mariſhes</hi> (That is Private ſtanding Churches that will not heare or admit of theſe Publick Preachers) <hi>ſhall not be healed but giuen to Salt. And by the Riuer on the banke thereof, on this ſide, and on that ſide, ſhall grow all Trees for meate, whoſe leafe ſhall not fade neither ſhall the Fruit thereof be conſumed:</hi> (that is Theſe Preachers ſhall not faile to make their conſtant monthly circuits out of their Citty) <hi>it ſhell bring forth new fruit according to his Months, becauſe the waters iſſued out of the Sanctuary, and the fruit thereof ſhall be for Meat, and the leafe thereof for medicine.</hi> Here The Goſpell very propely is Typefied by a River and by waters which cleanſe and purifies and heales all places, and makes every thing fruit full wherever they goe, Alſoe the Preachers are Typefied by Fiſhers, and by Trees, whoſe fruit ſerves both for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100647:6"/> food and Phyſick, in further confirmation of which, Heare what S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. John ſairh, <hi>And he ſhewed me a pure River of water of life cleare as Chriſt all proceeding out of the Throne of God and of the Lamb. In the midſt of the ſtreet of it; and of either ſide the River was there the Tree of life, which bare Twelve manner of Fruits, and yeilded her fruit every Month, and the leaves of the Trees were for the healing of the Nations.</hi> This ſeemes to be plaine in all the Circumſtances thereof, And therefore I haue taken the Modell and delineation of the Citty there from. But may be ſome may doubt whether The Throne of God be Jeruſalem. To which the Prophet Jerem: will anſwer for me, in the 3 cap &amp; 16 &amp; 17 verſes. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſse when ye be multiplyed and increaſed in the Land; in thoſe dayes ſaith the Lord, they ſhall ſay no more — The Arke of the Covenant of the Lord: neither ſhall it come to mind, neither ſhall they Remember it, neither ſhall they Viſite it, neither ſhall that be done any more. At that Time they ſhall call Jeruſalen</hi> The Throne of the Lord, <hi>and all the Nations ſhall by gathered unto it, to the Name of the Lord to Jeruſalem.</hi> As to the Fountaine I haue put in the middle to giue ſource to the Rivers. See what the Prophet Zach. ſaith the 13 cap. verſe 1. <hi>In that Day ſhall there be a Fountaine opened to the Houſe of Dauid for ſin and for unclea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And and a Fountaine ſhall come Forth of The Houſe of the Lord, and ſhall water the Valley of Shittim Ioell</hi> 3 <hi>&amp;</hi> 18: <hi>and Our Saviour ſaith in</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>: In<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 4 <hi>Cap. &amp;</hi> 14 <hi>verſe, Whoſoever ſhall drinke of the Water that I ſhall giue him, ſhall never thirſt. But the Water that I ſhall give him, ſhall be in him a Well of water ſpringing up into everlaſting life.</hi> The Watet which Chriſt will give, is the Water of the Goſpell, out of this Holy Fountaine, this holy Citty, And ſee how by the Prophet Iſaiah he inviteth all to theſe waters in the 55 cap. &amp; 1 vers. <hi>Ho, Every one that thirſteth, come ye to the Waters, and he that hath no mony: come ye buy and eat, yea come by wine and milke without money and without price.</hi> Many haue paid very deare for a draught of theſe Waters, But old things are paſſed away, and all things are become New. Theſe Evangelicall Preachers ſhall goe from Towne to Towne and from Citty to Citty, and are to offer theſe Waters of the Goſpell Gratis, inviteing all to come, and drink, and will not in the leaſt be chargeable to any one, being ſufficiently provided for from their Citty, with all things, neceſſary for their Function and voyage, <hi>If any man Thirſt let him come unto me and drink ſaith our Saviour</hi> John the 7. &amp; 37. and in the Rev: the 21. &amp; 6. <hi>I will giue him that is a thirſt of the Fountaine of the water of Life freely.</hi> And in the 22 cap. &amp; 17 verſe. <hi>And let him that is a thirſt come, and who ſoever will let him take the water of life freely.</hi> But then again as to the Preachers <hi>goeing to and fro,</hi> the following Texts ſeemes to be very favourable Gen. 28. &amp; 12. And hedreamed and be hold a Ladder ſet uppon the Earth, and the Top of it reached to Heaven. And behold the Angells of God aſcending and deſcending: Theſe Angells of God ſeeme to repreſent theſe Evangellicall Angells who from Heaven this New Jeruſalem are <hi>to goe to and fro,</hi> to doe Gods meſſage and to diſpence his word and bleſſing among the ſons
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100647:6"/> of men in each Land. And in Dan. the 12. &amp; 4. And thou ô Daniell ſhut up Theſe words, and ſeale up this, writeing to the Time of the End: What are Theſe words and this writeing which are to be ſealed up to the Time of the End? To me it ſeemes to be the enſueing ſentence which is a ſentence intire and independent of it ſelfe, haveing noe Relation either to the words goeing before or after viz<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Many ſhall goe to and fro and Knowledge ſhall be increaſed.</hi> That is from this New Jeruſalem many Preachers <hi>ſhall goe to and fro,</hi> inſtructing and preaching to the People, where by Knowledge ſhall be increaſed. But the Proph: Zacha ſeemes yet to be plainer both as to the manner of Theſe Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers goeing out, as alſoe to the happy Effect of Theit Doctrine in the 1 cap. &amp; 7 verſe, He ſaith thus, And I ſaw by night and behold a man rideing uppon a red horſe, and he ſtood among the Myrtle Trees, that were in the Bottome, and by him were red Horſes ſpeckled and white (for theſe Preachers to ride on) then ſaid I ô my Lord what are Theſe? And the Angell that talked with me, ſaid unto me I will ſhew thee what theſe be, And the Man that ſtood among the Myrtle trees, anſwered and ſaid theſe are they whom the Lord hath ſent to walke <hi>to and fro</hi> thorow the Earth (And now obſerue the happy Effects of their preaching,) And they anſwered the Angell of the Lord, that ſtood amongs the Myrtle Tees &amp; ſaid <hi>Wee Have walked to and fro thorow the Earth; And behold all the Earth ſitteth ſtill and is at Reſt.</hi> But leaſt it ſhould be doubted the office of theſe <hi>Walkers</hi> is not to ſettle peace and quietneſſe in the world, but onely to paſſe through and view the World, my ſence herein ſeemes to be confirmed in the 6 cap. &amp; 7 verſe, where ſpeakeing of Four Charriots ſent out From God, in the firſt of which were Red Horſes, in the ſecond Blacke, in the third white, in the fourth grizzled and Bay Horſes, tis ſaid, And the Bay went forth, and ſought to go, that they might <hi>walke to and fro</hi> thorow the Earth: And he ſaid get yet hence, <hi>Walke to, and fro,</hi> thorough the Earth. Then cryed he upon me and ſpake unto me, ſaying Behold Theſe that goe toward the North Country have <hi>Quieted</hi> my ſpirit in the North Country, ſoe that it ſeemes plaine to me that the office both of thoſe that rode on the Horſes, and in the Charrets, was to <hi>quiet</hi> the Earth. The Earth at Preſent hath much need of being quieted, Pray God of his merey ſend and Eſtabliſh Theſe <hi>To and fro Walkers.</hi> When they come Wee ſhall ſay as tis in the Proph. Iſaiah cap. 52. &amp; 7 vesſe. <hi>How Beautifull uppon the Mountaines are the Feete of thim that bringeth good Tideings that Publisheth Peace, that bringeth good Tideings of Good, that Publisherh Salvation, that ſaith unto Sion thy God Reigneth.</hi> I hope Theſe Arguments and Texts of Scripture carry ſuch a Face of probabillity uppon them as to perſwade any Perſon diſengaged from prejudice, to believe that a Holy Citty is to be build upon Earth, which is to Give birth to a New Adminiſtration. And Why may wee not beleeve that God may uſe the ſame OEconomie in His Church as he doth in the World, ſince what conduces to the good of one will alſoe conduce to the happineſſe of the other. The Earth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100647:7"/> is at it were paſſive, acted on by the Heavenly influences, the Sun the Moone and ſtarrs and all the Heavenly ſpheeres make Their continuall and conſtant circuits round it, adminiſtring their Light and heat, makeing day and night and differing ſeaſons, and impregnateing the dull matter ſoe as it may bring forth food both for man and beaſt in due ſeaſon. And wee find that Gods OEconomie in the Little World man, is the ſame as tis in the Great one. He makes his Blood and Spiritts to make their conſtant circuits, and thereby Keepes his Body in due frame and temper. This Spirituall OEconomie would procure the like effect, For this Citty would be as the Sun in the Firmament, or the Heart in Mans body, for as the Heart by continuall ſending forth blood and Spirits into all the Members of the Body procureth a perfect health; So Theſe Heavenly Preachers acting on the Dull minds of men, diſperſing their Heavenly influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as they goe, in a continuall ltineration and circulation through all the Cittyes and Villages of each Nation, would ſettle each Nation in perfect peace and Tranquillity. I haue ſaid each Nation, becauſe I believe that a Holy Citty will be built in each Nation. For though I beleeve that the Citty which the recalled Jewes will build in the Holy-Land will be the moſt Glorious Citty and more honoured by God then the Reſt, yet I beleeve not that ſhee is to be built and no other, Nor that ſhee is to have ſuperiority or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand ouer the Reſt, this would be to run backe into Aegipt and into the old Babyloniſh Captivity, and wee ſhould not better our ſelves, by the change of Adminiſtrations haueing onely changed Rome for Jeruſalem; Beſides to confine all power &amp; Dominon to one Citty or Nation, would be a weakneſſe that would fall much ſhort of that Perfection wee ſay this New OEconomie is to have, for one Citty or Nation cannot ſend out ſuch ſpeedy orders and commands as to ſerve the preſent neceſſityes and exigencyes of the whole World, eſpecially to the remoteſt Nations: The fall of Romes both Temporall and ſpirituall power, will convince ſuch a Government of Weakneſſe, ſoe that Jeruſalem I believe will onely haue the honour of an Elder ſiſter but noe more power then the Reſt. The Reſt Iſay, for I ſupoſe others, and that ſhee is not to be built alone, for that ſhe would not be able ſend out preachers to ſerue the neceſſityes of the whole world: I know very many promiſes are made to Jeruſalem, and I acknowledge that many are made to her in a particular manner, which ſhe alone ſhall enjoy. Yet notwithſtanding this, tis certaine, that moſt of the Promiſes made to her are made as to a part for the whole, and that the whole Church is interreſſed therein, there fore When the Proph: Zach<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. ſaith. And it ſhall be that who ſo will not come up of all the Familyes of the Earth to Jeruſalem to Worſhip the King the Lord of Hofts even uppon them ſhall he noe raine, I cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the meaneing of this to be, that all the World ſhould goe up to Jeruſalem in Paleſtine once a yeare, For ſome liue ſoe remote that they cannot goe thither and returne backe in a yeares Time, Nor doe I thinke that God would oblige all the world to ſo painefull a voyage. Yet I beleeve that when the Jewes are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100647:7"/> ſettled in their Land and haue built their Citty, <hi>zeale</hi> will draw up Perſons of all Nations to viſit their Land, I ſay <hi>zeale,</hi> to ſee that Land and People whom God hath bleſſed and not <hi>obligation</hi> will draw them up. And as to the obligation, When God ſaith that All Nations ſhall goe up to Jeruſalem to worſhip him there, I rather believe that Perſons of every Nation ſhall go up once a yeare to their <hi>owne</hi> Jeruſalem, I ſay ſome perſons and not all. For all muſt not be admitted to enter in it, onely ſuch as bring good Teſtimonialls of their Chriſtian Converſation and holy liueing. For David alludeing to this Holy Citty ſaith. Lord Who ſhall abide in thy Tabernacle? and who ſhall dwell in thy Holy Hill? He that walketh uprightly, and worketh righteouſneſſe and ſpeaketh the trueth in his heart. An S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. John ſaith There ſhall in noe wiſe enter into it any thing that defileth &amp;c. <hi>Bleſſed are they that do his commandments ehat they may haue Right to thee Tree of Life, and may enter in thorow the Gates into the Citty,</hi> For without are Dogges &amp;c. ſo that when God ſaith that all Nations ſhall come up to worſhip him at Jeruſalem, I underſtand by Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem all other Jeruſalems, as a part for the Whole, And by All Nations I underſtand Some of Every. Nation to repreſent all, And theſe Figures are very common in holy writ. But ſome will ſay that What the Proph. Dauid and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. John ſpeake of, is <hi>Heaven;</hi> in the ultimate degree and ſcope I allow it is heaven. But I contend earneſtly that wee muſt firſt haue the Types upon Earth. And what can Typifie Heaven better then a Holy Citty whoſe Inhabitans are to be Gods ſervants and Miniſters, repreſenting the Angells, and into which no impure thing, no unholy man ſhall enter, but ſuch as are of an unblemiſhed life and Converſation. But ſuppoſe it was Heaven abſolutly, I ſee not, but that the imitation of Things done in Heaven, here on Earth is very commendable.</p>
            <p>For the better Strengthening of the Propoſition of this my Holy Citty and New OEconomie I would further ſuggeſt the enſueing Conſiderations, That the Jewes as yet haue had no benifit of Our Saviours Death And are at Preſent a wretched miſerable People, under Gods diſpleaſure, diſperſed over the Face of the whole Earth. That the Chriſtians as yet haue had noe Settled or laſting Peace amongſt them ſince their embraceing ſo peaceable and holy a Religion: ſo that I think it will be eaſily granted me that the Religion of the Holy Jeſus has not as yet had it's proper and Naturall Effects upon Earth. And that all thoſe glorious promiſes of Juſtice, peace, and Truth, made by God to the Jewes in the old Teſtament, and to the Chriſtians in the New are not yet accompliſhed: And as I take it for granted that they are not yet accompliſhed, ſo I more cert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ainly take it for granted that they <hi>will</hi> be; for all the promiſes of God are <hi>Yea and Amen.</hi> It cannot enter into my Mind that the Son of God ſhould come into the world, and take upon him humane Nature and preach unto Mankind. And that the World ſhould remaine in the Same unhappie circumſtances of War and miſery as it was before. Tis true I know he ſaith that he came not to ſend peace into the world but a Sword. But this he ſpeakes of the accidentall
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100647:8"/> effect of his doctrine and not the naturall. His doctrine has noe ſuch innate propenſity in it ſelfe, but ſuch Evill Effects come <hi>ab extra</hi> Wee may with great Juſtice therefore Expect the naturall Effects of Chriſts doctrine upon Earth. God hath promiſed it, and very pathetically deſcribes the ſtate of its accidentall Effects, and its Naturall in the 8 cap. of Zach<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. and beginning at the 10 verſe. ſaith He. <hi>Before Theſe dayes</hi> (ſpeakeing of this New OEconomia) <hi>there was no hire for man, nor any hire for beaſt, neither was there any Peace to him that went out, or came in, becauſe of affliction: for I ſet all men every one againſt his Neighbour. But now I will not be unto the Reſidue of this People, as in the former dayes ſaith the Lord of Hofts. For the ſeed ſhall be proſperous: The vine ſhall giue her fruit, and the Ground ſhall giue her encreaſe, And the Heavens ſhall giue their dew, and I will cauſe the Remnant of this Teople to poſeſſe all theſe things.</hi> It has beene the Expectation of many devout and Pious Chriſtians for this Laſt hundred yeares, to ſee the Propheſyes and Promiſes of God fullfilled, to ſee the Jewes converted, the Church in a moſt Flourishing condition, and Peace Truth and Juſtice Eſtablished upon Earth: But their Expectations haue failed them; and wee are ſtill in the darke: ſo that the Preſent Times ſeemes to be that Dunkell Day Spoaken of by the Proph. Zach<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. Knowne onely to the Lord, in w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>. it ſhould be neither Day nor night but ſaith that in the Evening there ſhould be Light: which is of great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>freſhment to al thoſe good Soules who waite for this bleſſed evening. It muſt be confeſſed, that tis neither Day nor night with us, Wee haue waited and looked up and calculated, and all our calculations haue bene Erroneous But notwithſtanding wee haue erred yet God cannot miſtake, he is true<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and will certainly ſend forth his Light and his Truth in due Time; For the Writeings of the Prophets are not as waſt paper, or the Fables of Poets, but the reall dictates of the Spirit of God. Men There fore may with great reaſon Expect Glorious and happy Times becauſe God hath promiſed them, their Expectation is good and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable but nothing elſe. For they neither rightly enquire into the Nature of thinges, Nor are fitted to receiue any ſuch Mercyes. Firſt Iſay they make not right Enquiry into things. Tis true they may depend wpon God to fulfill his owne promiſes, Yet they ought a little to inſpect into the meanes, For God workes all his purpoſes, by juſt and propper Mediums; Glorious Times are expected, But wee ought to ſay How? by which wayes? and methods, and from what ſpring will they haue their originall? the naturall Anſwer hereto will be by <hi>changeing</hi> ſomething, this ought next therefore be enquired into viz<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. on what Bottom and Ground the Naturall and Pollitical Conſtitution of this World ſtands: And ſince Theſe Happy Times are to come by <hi>Changes,</hi> Wee ought dilligently to find out Thoſe things which will admitt of a <hi>change,</hi> and thoſe things which will not, And this will facilitate the worke and make us more eaſily comply with thoſe Mediums and Propoſitions which are amongſt the changeable predicaments. The Things the refore here below
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100647:8"/> that are unchangeable for brevitys ſake I shall comprehend under Seaven Heads as foll<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Life and Death.</item>
               <item>2. Pleaſure and paine.</item>
               <item>3. Buiſneſſe under which may be comprehended the inequallity of Perſons and Differing Intreſts of Men.</item>
               <item>4. The Faculty of Chooſeing, under which may be comprehended the paſſions and affections of Men.</item>
               <item>5. Diuine Worship and Love to our Neighbour.</item>
               <item>6. Juſtice.</item>
               <item>7. Power. Theſe are all <hi>Eſſentiall</hi> and perpetuall, conſtituting the naturall and Politicall Adminiſtration of this World, And to take a way any of theſe is to pull downe the pillars of the Earth. It muſt therefore be granted me that what ever things are changed in order to pocure the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Times Theſe muſt continue in <hi>ſtatu qno.</hi> Then 2<hi rend="sup">dly</hi>.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The things that are changeable are onely Three viz<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Minds and opinions of Men.
<list>
                     <item>Theſe are <hi>Acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talia</hi> and mutable, And whatſoever changes may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in order to the produceing of Happy Times can onely be in theſe Three.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. The Outward Adminiſtration of Juſtice and Power.</item>
               <item>3. The Outward Adminiſtration of Diuine Worship.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt I need not Prove that the opinions of Men are changeable, it being ſufficiently Knowne, And ſince the World in a manner is Governed by opinion, and it has ſo great power &amp; influence over men, It muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity follow that the abolition of many corrupt and bad opinions which at preſent diſturb the peace of the World, and the admiſſion of new ones, more conduceing to its welfare and happineſſe; will make up a great part of that felicity which is expected in the change of affaires. Secondly I need not prove that the outward Adminiſtration of Juſtice and Power are changeable. The Names of Deſpoticke, Monarchick, mixt, Ariſtocraticke, Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craticke, being the preſent Inſcriptions on theſe Soveraine Metalls will eaſily convince this. Nor will I mention which of theſe Methods of Government is beſt, Severall Nations haueing beene happy under all of them. And laſtly I shall haue as Little occaſion to prove that the outward Adminiſtration of Diuine Worship is changeable, for nothing is more apparent in holy Scripture then this; There has beene a ſeries of mutations, from Noah to Abraham, from Abraham to Moſes, from Moſes to Soloman, from Solomon to Our Saviour, and from Our Saviour to this day: And Theſe things being well conſidered I hope the New way of Eccleſiaſticall Adminiſtration propoſed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100647:9"/> will be more eaſily admitted: The Preſent Adminiſtration in all Countryes is differing, and very unhappy, eſpecially in England God he Knowes! But this moſt exquiſite and uniforme Way I Haue propoſed will cure all Evills the World Labours under on this acco<hi rend="sup">tt</hi>. But more of this hereafter. I ſaid before that I found men Expecting to receiue the Benifit of happy Times, but noe way willing to comply with any Reaſonable propoſitions that might introduce them. The Greek, the Roman, the Lutheran, the Reformed, the English, and all other private and particular Churches, would have their owne opinions, and particular Method of Adminiſtration be eſtablished Throughout the World. And Iam ſattisfied that when God shall begin to worke his deſignes and fullfill his promiſes made to the Sons of Men, that they will not be more content Then the Jewes was with Our Saviour, they will think it should be ſomething elſe, And thinke all should be done after their <hi>owne</hi> way. But alas! they are mightily miſtaken, For heare what God ſaith by his Prophet Iſaiah. <hi>For my Thoughts are not your Thoughts, neither are your wayes my wayes ſaith the Lord, For as ths Heavens are higher then the Earth ſo are my Wayes, higher then your wayes, and my Thoughts then your Thoughts.</hi> The Jewes ſent the Prophet Jerim<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. to enquire of God for them what they should do, and made a Proteſtation to obey what ever should be commanded them, yet when the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand came they refuſed to be obedient, and cleaved to their <hi>owne</hi> wayes and to the imagination of their owne heart. So it is with us Wee ſay in our Prayers <hi>thy Kingdome come thy will be done in Earth as it is Heaven,</hi> And pray and Expect Glorious Times, yet for all our hopes, and Prayers Wee would have our <hi>owne</hi> Kingdoms, Our <hi>owne</hi> will, and our owne wayes be done upon Earth notwithſtanding whatever wee may ſeeme to wish or deſire. Great was the hopes and Expectation of the Jewes of a Saviour, And when they had him they crucified him. And Iam ſattisfied should he come againe in the flesh to the Chriſtians, in the ſame humble manner as he did to the Jewes and preach againſt Some of their evill Cuſtomes and Conſtitutions, The Chriſtians (Notwithſtanding their preſent adoration of him in heaven) would as certainly crucifie him as did the Jewes: for the Nature of mankind is in all places and at all times much the Same, Whoever croſſes their humour or intreſt or ſpeak againſts any thing in which they have beene edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated shall certainly find ill treatment. Our Saviour pulled downe the Jewish OEconomie but it coſt him his Life, And the Apoſtles and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs extinguished the fire on the Heathen Altars, but it was with their Blood, And whoever ſpeakes againſt the bad cuſtomes and conſtitutions of the Chriſtians no doubt but will find his share of miſery. But Gods will be done. But then further ſince Every Denomination of Chriſtians, haue a differing way of Adminiſtration, And ſince there are many partyes, and that every party would haue their owne way be preferd and to be eſtablished in the world before all others; What Remedy is there for theſe things?
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100647:9"/> to ſet up any particular way before the other will not do well, for that will inflame and provoke the oppoſition of all the Reſt. The onely remedy therefoe is to ſet up a way differing from all, whereby all being pulled downe and none in particular ſet up or preferred before the other, None will have reaſon to complaine. And ſuch is the way of Adminiſtration I propoſe, tis different from all their wayes, nay and it is <hi>Gods way</hi> to, as I plainely prove by Scripture, and then no wonder tis differing from Mens wayes. For as I ſaid before, God ſaith my Wayes are not like your wayes. But in order to conclude I shall ſpeake a little of the advantages of this Adminiſtration.</p>
            <p>Suppoſeing therefore in Each Kingdome and Nation a Citty built in the midſt thereof, Bleſſed God! What a Glorious change ſhould wee Sudenly See in the World? What a Bleſſed Harmony would there be betwixt theſe Holy and chaſt Siſters? The Bleſſed Effects of this OEconomie is allmoſt unſpeakable, All thoſe Evills the World Labours under on Account of Religion, would ſpeedily vaniſh like the morning dew before the ſun. Upon the building of theſe, all the old ill built Fabricks would fall to the ground. Firſt the Man of Sin would tumble from his Throne like Dagon before the Ark, And how Happy and eaſy would the Princes of Chriſtendom find themſelves, when rid of all his Eccleſiaſticall pretenſions. They and their Kingdomes haue tomuch Suffered by his greevous yoke and unjuſt uſurpations (I need not Quote old ſtoryes Wee haue a certaine King at preſent ſtruggling in the Eccleſiaſtical Net) But this OEconomie would abſolutely free them for ever from all the Scourgeing of the Eccleſiaſticall whip: And wee should heare no more of Popes Kicking downe of Emperours Crownes, Thundering out Curſes, forbidding the Subject to pay his Homage to his Lawfull Prince: All the Doleful noiſe of Perſecution would be no more heard of in the World. All ſects and partyes, would ſpeedily vaniſh, And wee ſhould haue no more Flying for Religion, from one Country to another the Proteſtants from France or Papiſts from England; No Kingdom or Country turned upſide downe by Religious Men, contending to get or keep their partyes in, and to turne others out of the Government. For theſe preachers being Sufficiently provided for in thir reſpectiue Cittyes, all Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of acting irregularly would be taken away. And by this meanes Temporalls would be abſolutely Seperated from Spiritualls A thing much hitherto wiſhed for but never yet effected, And wee should heare no more of Kings impriſoning Bishops, or of Bishops dethroneing Kings, nor of this or that Party being upper or under in the Government, For theſe Spirituall preachers should haue nothing to do in any Government, Nor should Princes or Temporall Power haue anything to doe in ſpiritualls, for this has beene the occaſion of many Evills in the World, and has corrupted the purity of the Chriſtian doctrine, And a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine King hath ſaid, ſo long as it was in his power ſo chooſe Biſhops he could haue what Goſpell he pleaſed, Therefore theſe ſpirituall Men, in reſpectiue their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100647:10"/> Cittyes, (as in another place I haue ſaid) are to be choſen by Lot as was Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias, And hereby God as is moſt Iuſt and fit will chooſe his owne Miniſters and Servants, and then no doubt but wee shall haue the Stream to run pure. And theſe Streams comeing out from this Holy Citty every Month, how will they coole and refresh each Nation, there will be no dry or barren Corners therein But all things will liue, and all places be Green and flourishing where theſe liueing waters come. At preſent by the unhappyneſſe of the preſenr Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, many are the Darke Corners of the World, where the Light of the Goſpell shines not, and no proviſion is made for Preachers. But Theſe Goſpell Angells, theſe Rayes of the Sun, will illuminate all the Darke Corners of Each Land, ſo that <hi>The Earth will be full of the Knowledge of the Lord as the Waters cover the Sea;</hi> No dry or barren corners will want watering by theſe <hi>ever Flowing Fountaines</hi> And no Dark corners want the Rayes of theſe glorious and <hi>everſhinning Ligbts.</hi> But Iam not able to deſcribe all the advantages of this moſt Excellent OEconomie but muſt ſend you to the Prophets who doe it very largely and pathetically.</p>
            <p>Theſe things wee Suppoſe will come to paſſe to make up the fulneſſe of the Gentiles which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul ſpeakes of, But then as to the Iewes may I ſpeake in the Termes of the Angell, in the 12 vers of the 1: cap. of Zacha. who when the men had brought in their Report That all the Gentiles were Still and at Reſt, ſaid, O Lord of Hoſts how long wilt thou not haue mercy on Jeruſalem &amp;c. Without all doubt God will Remember his promiſes made to the Jewes by the mouth of all his Prophets, and will bring them and Eſtablish them in their Owne Land, Where they will build alſo a Citty holy to the Lord, out which will flow <hi>Liueing Waters</hi> (viz<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Peachers) <hi>halfe of them toward the Former Sea and halfe of them toward the hinder Sea, both in Summer and in Winter,</hi> as both the Proph: Zach<hi rend="sup">a</hi>: and Ezek: mention: And Paleſtine being placed in the <hi>midſt</hi> of the Earth, (as ſome Writers affirme) And Jeruſalem built in the <hi>midſt</hi> of Paleſtine, And a Jeruſalem or Holy Citty built in the <hi>midſt</hi> of Each Kingdome, How will every thing answer one another? Ye Admirers of order, Ye Sons of Uniformity, Where can there be greater order and Uniformity then in ſuch an OEconomie? What a glorious Harmony will there be betwixt Theſe Holy and chaſt Siſters Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem in Paleſtine being the firſt borne? How Glorious will the Spouſe of Chriſt be in ſuch Dayes? <hi>Let us be glad and Rejoyce, and giue honour to him: For the marriage of the Lamb is come, and his wife hath made herſelfe ready.</hi> I dare not affirme with what particular preſence and manner God will Honour theſe Cittyes, But it is ſaid that <hi>the Lamb will be the Light there of.</hi> And what if God should Honour theſe Cittyes of the Gentiles, with the ſame honour with which he honoured the Tabernacle and Temple of the Jewes? Who can tell? Great are his mercyes to his unworthy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. In our Dayly Prayers Wee beg of God that <hi>his Kingdom may come</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:100647:10"/> 
               <hi>and that his will may be done on Earth as it is in Heaven,</hi> But I pray you tell me, was there ever a Kingdome without Cittyes? will a Few Houſes make a Kingdom? God has Houſes in the Earth, tis true, but as yet has no Cittyes Therefore if wee would haue his <hi>Kingdome come</hi> Wee muſt build him Cittyes. And when in Each Kingdom he has <hi>a Citty</hi> built, they <hi>all together</hi> will make him here on Earth a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> or at Leaſtwiſe by their influence make the whole Earth his <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo our Prayers <hi>of thy Kingdome</hi> come, will be fullfilled, both in a Literal and in a ſpirituall Sence. And as Other Kings of the Earth, amongſt all their Cities do chooſe one for the Royall ſeat of their Kingdome, ſo God will chooſe Jeruſalem, and put his <hi>Throne</hi> there, and make it as it were the Head of this ſpirituall Kingdome. The Prophet Ierem. ſaith at that Time they shall call Jeruſalem The <hi>Throne of the Lord,</hi> And all Nations shall be gathered unto it. And the Proph. Mic<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. ſaith in the 4 cap. &amp; 8 verſe. And thou O Tower of Flock &amp;c. unto Thee shall <hi>it come,</hi> even the <hi>Firſt Dominion, The Kingdom shall come,</hi> to the Daughter of Jeruſalem. Here it is ſaid that shee shall haue the <hi>Firſt Dominion,</hi> And that the Kingdom (which we haue ſo often begg'd for) shall come to her, Wee know tis the Cuſtome on Earth, that the Eldeſt Son or daughter shall Inherite the Crowne, Now God has here a <hi>ſpirituall Kingdom,</hi> And theſe Cittyes or Severall Churches are his <hi>daughters,</hi> But Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem is the Eldeſt: Now to which of the Daughters should the <hi>Kingdome come?</hi> God here anſwers, To Thee (as the Eldeſt) shall it come, even the <hi>Firſt Dominion,</hi> the Kingdom shall come to the <hi>Daughter</hi> of Jeruſalem. But Theſe Words the <hi>Firſt Dominion,</hi> may admit of a double conſtruction, Firſt they may imply that all theſe Cityes, ſiſters, or Daughters, are to haue <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion</hi> But that the Holy Citty built at Jeruſalem as the <hi>Firſt</hi> and Eldeſt Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter shall haue The <hi>Firſt</hi> or principall Dominion, or they may ſignifie that all theſe Siſters, as Gods Daughters may haue a <hi>right</hi> to the Dominion and the Kingdome, But that the Citty at Jeruſalem as eldeſt Daughter shall haue the Dominion firſt, And the others afterward Succeſſively, Whether of theſe are the more genuine I leave to the more Judicous to determine, But for the Reaſons formerly mentioned I think not that the Nature of this Dominion is Imperiall, or that the Lady at Jeruſalem, should as a Queen Exercize an abſolute command ouer the Reſt, But I rather thinke that the nature of it rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes more to order than command, And that shee shall haue a Priority of order and preheminence of Reſpect due to her on acco<hi rend="sup">tt</hi>. of being Eldeſt Siſter, and as enjoying more particular honours and favours from God.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſſe I have found this Little Booke in the inditeing or eating of it as Sweet as hony, I hope that no one hereafter will make it bitter in my Belly, For I have wrote Nothing but for what I have alleadged the Word of God and Great probabillity. The Apoſtle ſaith <hi>there are different Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations, but one Lord.</hi> The Lord is King of the Univerſe, And Chriſt is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100647:11"/> the Head Adminiſtrator, and can Governe his Family after what method and manner he pleaſes: What therefore if he firſt order an Altar, then a Tabernacle, then a Temple, and then a Citty, And then at Laſt bring us to Heaven the <hi>New Jeruſalem it ſelfe.</hi> The Prophet David ſaith, They shall paſſe from ſtrength to ſtrength untill they come to God in Sion: <hi>Heaven it ſelfe</hi> without a Type, To which Place God of his infinite mercy bring us all through the merits of Jeſus Chriſt Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>The Julian and Gregorian Account of <hi>Time</hi> are both vitious and puts the world in no ſmall confuſion. I would therefore humbly propoſe that they both may be regulated by an exact calculation. It will not onely be the greateſt <hi>honour,</hi> but alſo the greateſt <hi>Proffet</hi> and advantage to that King or Prince Who shall undertake ſo Honourable a Task. Since therefore <hi>all things are to be come New,</hi> And the Angell ſaith that <hi>Time</hi> shall be no more (which I underſtand to be the Time of the old Adminiſtation, as alſo of the Old Vitious calculation) I hope that this Propoſition will alſo be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that with the <hi>New</hi> Adminiſtration, wee may haue a <hi>New</hi> account of Time That wee may write <hi>Anno domi, &amp; Anno ab Urbe conditâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100647:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
